<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COMM-260 Quant Methods &amp; Data Viz (Fall 2021)</title>
    <description>Final projects from students in Quantitative Methods &amp; Data Visualization at American University Fall 2020.  
</description>
    <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 11:06:16 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 11:06:16 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Good for Goodreads: Reading Grows in Popularity amid COVID-19 Pandemic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;She sat in her room, and watched the pile of books grow larger, week after week of remaining stuck in the house. Reading was everything, it was her way of maintaining a routine and keeping sane amidst unprecedented times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Murphy, 20, a junior attending The College of New Jersey, has always considered herself an avid reader, and staying in her house in her small town of Harrington Park during the spring of 2020 and the initial outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic, she found immense comfort in one of her oldest interestsÑlosing herself in a book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Obviously quarantine was an incredibly difficult and stressful time for most people,” Murphy said, nodding to her friend casually sitting beside her. “I found myself reading frequently as a way to manage everything going on in the world and keep things from feeling too overwhelming.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many others, Ryan Murphy supplemented her reading with Goodreads, the worldÕs largest site for readers and book recommendations, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/about/us&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;. Goodreads allows its users to review, rate, and recommend books, all while connecting with their peers. The rating feature is what is most attractive to users, according to Murphy, as they can rate books from one to five. Along with that, they can write their own review, and then view and comment on other users reviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, specifically during the height of quarantine in March and April, Goodreads users had a hugely positive spike, gaining around 105,000 users in April 2020 alone, according to data from a sample of Goodreads users put into a Global Book Reading Dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Goodreads users 2019 vs 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-s2OV2&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/s2OV2/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rating feature is what is most attractive to users, according to Murphy, as they have the opportunity to rate books from one to five. Along with that, they can write their own review, and then view and comment on other users reviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Rating books is the best part of Goodreads,” Murphy exclaimed. She pulled up her Goodreads and scrolled though, showing off the numerous books she has rated, ranging across multiple different genres. “ItÕs a huge motivator to finish a book, especially since I know that I can see what people say and they can see what I write.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books like the Harry Potter series, The Hunger Games, and Twilight, have amassed some of the most user reviews, with all of them obtaining around 40,000 reviews, according to a dataset of Goodreads user rating data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-scatter&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/8060044&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodreads has had a strong presence for years, but more people were attracted to it as the pandemic grew in severity. Sofia Brockman, 20, a student at American University, considered herself a big reader earlier in her life, but as she got older, she found herself gravitating towards other hobbies, therefore reading less and less. She had heard about Goodreads in July of 2021 and found the idea of a social platform for reading very appealing, according to Brockman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was attracted to the idea of sharing my thoughts and being able to find friends and discuss books with them on this platform,” Brockman said. “ItÕs like a really big book club, and the sense of community is really comforting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brockman excitedly explained the features of Goodreads she enjoyed the most, specifically the reading challenge. The Goodreads yearly reading challenge allows users to create a goal for themselves and participate with their friends. The social aspect of Goodreads allows for users to join groups, ranging from science fiction to Taylor Swift Lyrics that relate to books, according to Brockman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Brockman, Kelli Pastor, 51, from Layton New Jersey, had not heard of Goodreads until relatively recently. She has been reading for most of her life and has been a member of multiple different book clubs, one of which was focused entirely on reading and analyzing War and Peace by Leo Tolstoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I first heard of Goodreads when I went to my local bookstore,” Pastor said. There was a display table featuring “BookTok favorites” and “Goodreads Discussion Starters” and upon seeing she went home and looked up those unfamiliar terms, according to Pastor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Social Media and reading were never intertwined in my mind,” Pastor exclaimed. “It is such a foreign concept to me, but I feel that it will be very beneficial in re-engaging readers, especially those of a younger generation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With COVID-19, more and more people spent time inside, and like Brockman, they had the free time to discover new interests. There was a rise in social media presence, with TikTok in particularly experiencing massive growth. TikTok appealed to so many different groups of people, as everyone can find a niche to express themselves, according to Brockman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imogen Angel, 19, a sophomore at American University, became familiar with Goodreads through TikTok Ñshe created an account after receiving many book recommendations via TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BookTok, a sect of TikTok, emerged in during COVID, and was an important factor in the growth of Goodreads, according to Angel. “BookTokers,” as the influencers who grew from promoting books, have been called, would use Goodreads to connect with their followers, encouraging them to join the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I ultimately made the account in order to follow the reviews of the influencers I found on TikTok,Ó Angel exclaimed. ÒThey created groups on Goodreads for their followers to join, and the book recommendations have been amazing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Angel, reading is an important form of expression, like those across the world who joined Goodreads during the pandemic. From February 2020 to September 2020, Goodreads had users join from 229 different countries, spanning each continent, with Antarctica being the exception, according to a dataset of a sample of Goodreads users that joined the site during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that same period, 48.8 percent of users that joined were female, with 38.7 percent being male and 12.4 percent not identifying within that binary according to that same dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Goodreads Users Who Joined During the PandemicÊ&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-n7Alh&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/n7Alh/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;380&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodreads reaches and attracts such a large group, according to Angel. The app is an ever-growing community that continues to evolve and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Murphy, Goodreads provides an excitement that reading has not had for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is so much potential for the future of Goodreads,Ó Murphy said. ÒI canÕt wait to keep reading and finding others who share my passion.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/goodreads-covid-19/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/goodreads-covid-19/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>For DC Restaurants, the Pandemic Persists</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Marr checked his tattered leather watch. It was 6:30 p.m. on a Friday, and his pizza spot should have been filling up with hungry families, yet only a quarter of the restaurant was occupied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tenleytown location of Pete’s New Haven Style Pizza survived the pandemic by adapting to its customers’ safety needs and delivery demand, but months after other business sectors regained strength the restaurant has still not reached its past level of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re ready for them and we need them,” said Marr. “We’ve got the staff and supplies, but the customers just won’t come,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some return to normalcy, the DC restaurant industry currently lags far behind the national restaurant industry in its recovery from the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.dc.gov/data/vaccination&quot;&gt;80% of the city partially or fully vaccinated&lt;/a&gt;, many sectors of business have almost fully returned to their 2019 levels of contribution to the district’s GDP, according to the Bureau of Economic Analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local food and beverage sector is far from its past revenue, and analysis has little hope for a quick recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data recorded by the online reservation service OpenTable shows how in-person dining has changed by comparing this year’s rates to those before the pandemic. Although in-person dining is at a national low, the district remains around 30% lower than this average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Weekly Seated Diners&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-mmJWU&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/mmJWU/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivery services have replaced much of this lost business, theorizes the reservation service. Other economic indicators, however, demonstrate that this substitute is not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loan analysis company LendingTree &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lendingtree.com/business/best-places-to-open-a-restaurant/&quot;&gt;published its own analysis&lt;/a&gt; of five market metrics to predict the likelihood of restaurant recovery in major US cities, and placed Washington, DC at the very bottom of its list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to its large decrease in consumer spending in restaurants, industry employment and other factors, the analysis predicts that the nation’s capital is least likely to regain its strength in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LendingTree chief credit analyst Matt Schulz stated that larger, more expensive cities are inherently difficult places for restaurants to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The sheer amount of restaurant options that are available in those areas plays a big role,” said Schulz. “That’s true even in the best of times. Factor in a pandemic, and it all just gets exponentially more difficult,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many national attempts to preserve the food and beverage sector have proved to be lifelines for restaurants in the district. The Paycheck Protection Program and Restaurant Revitalization Fund gave nearly a billion dollars to restaurants, bars, and food counters in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Restaurant Revitalization Fund Grant Recipients&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-3aYBU&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/3aYBU/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;731&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money from the RRF, a subsidiary of the Small Business Administration, does not need to be paid back. The funds can be used for payroll, rent and other business expenses until March of 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“RRF money was a saving grace,” said manager Ben Noval as he motioned to the outdoor seating the funds helped purchase at his Dupont Circle restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noval was forced to lay off 14 of his colleagues and close friends at the outset of the pandemic and has only been able to hire back eight of them. To date, the pandemic has caused over 30,000 job losses in Washington restaurants, according to the Bureau for Labor Statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can barely keep up with the little business that we’re getting,” said Noval. “Now is the time that we need more staff, and now is the time that we need more funding,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Restaurant Association has been extensively campaigning for more federal money to be put into the RRF and redistributed before the end of the year. Little movement in congress has been caused by the requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locally, the Restaurant Association of Metropolitan Washington has been providing relief to laid off industry workers through a donation based fund. With no financial ability to help entire restaurants, RAMW supports the National Restaurant Association’s advocacy and tries to increase the sense of community between restaurants in the district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sense of community is what both Marr and Noval believe has kept the industry alive throughout the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Restaurants, especially those owned by minorities, are very connected to one another,” said Noval. “Competition is very real, of course, but we’re all in this together,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/8039961&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washington restaurants that received RRF grants had one of the highest percentages of female-owned restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationally, restaurants employ more minority managers than any other industry, according to the National Restaurant Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These minority-owned restaurants unofficially banded together during the pandemic to help one another, reported restaurant workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Little Ethiopia’ on U and 9th street has become a culinary hotspot for all Washington residents and witnessed this community action first hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restaurants of the Shaw corner were hit hard by the pandemic, forcing many to close their doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaleb Tswafe moved to Washington from Ethiopia several years ago and began chasing memories from home in the kitchens of the area. He quickly learned to love Little Ethiopia, and was distraught when the pandemic forced many restaurants to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You can see people running produce across the street to their competition,” Tswafe said. “That’s something you’ll only get between two Ethiopian restaurants and that’s the way out of this mess,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost none of these restaurants received any federal loans or grants, and have relied on their communities for relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a problem affecting all the restaurants here and we’ve gotta fix it,” said Tswafe. “We’re not far from healed but we’ll get there together,”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:44:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/pandemic-restaurants-dc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/pandemic-restaurants-dc/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More Tax and Less Pay</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That red-stained underwear. That warm, oozy, scary sensation. The embarrassment, the frustration, the “why am I a woman?” feeling. A period is no small feat for the population that menstruates. But on top of the emotional stress that those who menstruate go through, they are still paying a substantial amount of money –in some states even extra– for something so fundamentally necessary. It’s time we talk about the tampon tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the irrationally high cost, feminine hygiene products have an added tax, called the tampon tax, that takes away one to two dollars annually from an individual women’s earning in 27 states. Coincidentally, the states that charge women more for menstrual products are also the states in which women earn significantly less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/8060626/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; class=&quot;flourish-embed-iframe&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/8060626/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/8060626&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/8013087/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; class=&quot;flourish-embed-iframe&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/8013087/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/8013087&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darker pink shading on the map on the left shows the higher rates of tampon tax. These coincide with the lighter green shading in the map on the right showing lower overall annual women’s earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women are expected to pay higher taxes on products specifically made for them in some states even though they are paid less. But is a dollar or two really worth fighting for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.periodequity.org/&quot;&gt;Period Equity&lt;/a&gt; Laura Strausfeld, though the numbers seem small, they do add up. On average women spend about &lt;a href=&quot;https://swnsdigital.com/us/2019/11/new-research-reveals-how-much-the-average-woman-spends-per-month-on-menstrual-products/&quot;&gt;159 dollars a year&lt;/a&gt; just on period products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strausfeld believes that the key to bringing down economic barriers for people who menstruate and need these products is for everybody, especially those who don’t menstruate to understand the nature of menstruation. The most effective way to do that: by openly talking about menstruation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hashtaghappyperiod.org/&quot;&gt;HappyPeriod&lt;/a&gt; Chelsea VonChaz believes that the best way to increase awareness of period poverty and menstrual inequity is for people who menstruate to start feeling more comfortable talking about their periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The main social factor is that the people, folks who are not assigned female at birth that have never had a period and will never have a period just don’t understand menstruation and they’re just ignorant and very comfortable in their ignorance and within that, choose to make it harder for folks that have a period and there’s no space for [the ignorant] to learn,” said VonChaz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Race and Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strausfeld and VonChaz touch on a topic that has seemed almost taboo. What about culture, race and ethnicity? Yes, those influence our conversation, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/8074655/embed&quot; title=&quot;Interactive or visual content&quot; class=&quot;flourish-embed-iframe&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;flourish-credit&quot; href=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/8074655/?utm_source=embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/8074655&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration:none!important&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Made with Flourish&quot; src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the map shows, the four states that tax the most (up to 2 dollars) stayed very near the median percent of the people who identify as white in a population (77 per cent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When it comes to ethnicities and race, I do see more of a freedom amongst people who identify as white talking about their periods, experiencing their periods and also being more advanced when it comes to their menstrual care than folks who are non-whites,” said VonChaz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are culturally more reluctant to talk openly about menstruation. “But that is changing due to youth activists who are open and loud about how natural menstruation is and what the needs are of people who menstruate,” said Strausfeld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with founders of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/letsperiodtalk/&quot;&gt;Period Talk&lt;/a&gt; Kuhu Badgi, Akshika Chawade and Niki Murthy, the three agreed that, even in the younger generations, talking about periods is vital to the de-stigmatization of menstruation. And sometimes using social media also goes a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we realized that it was really as simple as like making a TikTok video. Like that was something that was a really effective way to reach an audience of people and show them or just make the conversation a lot easier to talk about,” said Badgi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Strausfeld and VonChaz say that it is important for people who menstruate to help those who do not understand what menstruation is and why the need for more easily accessible period products is a pressing issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health care&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the levels of women insured changes only slightly between the states that do and don’t implement the tampon tax, there is a trend that states with no tax have a smaller percent of women who have health insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Population of Women with Health Insurance&quot; aria-label=&quot;Range Plot&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-juGaQ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/juGaQ/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;1125&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}(); &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An experience quite common among those who menstruate is having a period at school and not knowing what to do. Whether it is their first period, whether they completely forgot about their period, or if they just don’t have a pad, tampon, menstrual cup, etc. with them, it is always a frustrating and unnecessarily scary situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is harder for girls to gather the courage to go to the nurse’s office at school if they need a period product than if they were readily accessible in the bathrooms. But that starts with education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking down the stigmas around periods can save a lot of young girls from trauma or embarrassment. As the struggle for public places to provide free menstrual products continues, Von Chaz says, “it takes for us to eliminate the tax, then push for politicians to make sure that period products are accessible in spaces like courthouses, shelters, transition homes, prisons, schools, libraries, etc.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Female Educational Attainment&quot; aria-label=&quot;Split Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-VHwj5&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/VHwj5/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;1499&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}(); &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, the states that have higher tampon taxes are also those who tend to have a lower average percentage of women earning bachelor’s degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But part of the efforts is educating everyone, not just those who menstruate. Even as high schoolers, Badgy, Chawade and Murthy have experienced he uncomfortableness that can come from trying to explain the issue with people who don’t menstruate, especially in the older generations. Talking about the pitch competitions that launched Period Talk, Chawade said, “so [the judges] were unable to truly grasp the gravity of the problem we were trying to tackle… It was just very hard to like explain the problem to somebody who has like zero experience with menstruation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yes. Period poverty is a real thing. Having outrageously high prices on menstrual products and charging an extra tax on them does affect the poverty rate amongst females.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only a matter of building up confidence and community by raising awareness, one period at a time. Period.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:43:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/tax-feminine-products/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/tax-feminine-products/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where Did The Gay Bars Go?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The smell of fresh paint floats around the room as the walls slowly change color, stroke by stroke. The unmistakable hum of a drill installing the thick, soft, and regal theater curtains on the windows upstairs. The sizzle of the flattop in the kitchen, while they work on the perfect breakfast sandwich recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rach Pike, 36, and Jo McDaniel, 40, have been working on creating the As You Are Bar on the corner of Eighth and E for some time now.  Listening to them talk about it, you’d think that they were born to do this- and based on their history, they kind of were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Pike and McDaniel just came from past jobs in LGBTQ night life and are fierce advocates for all in the community. Rach worked as the head of security, and Jo as the former general manager, at A League Of Her Own lesbian bar in Adams Morgan, when they realized they could make their own space. They could make a space for everyone in the LGBTQ community, regardless of how others saw the space should be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wanted better, and I didn’t know if anyone else could do it.”  McDaniel explained as she looked out at the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All the things that are all the imperfections. So we started to recognize them and also started to say like, well, let’s handle this. We’ve got the time, right?” Rach added as they looked at Jo, as a smile grew on both of their faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of gay bars and clubs in Washington, DC has been, at least on a data perspective- perplexing. Growing from 7 bars and clubs in 1980 (the hay day of gay nightlife culture)  to 15 in 2021, it looks as if gay bars and clubs are here to stay. For Washington, they might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Gay Bars in DC in 1980&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-2H0kk&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/2H0kk/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;753&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Gay Bars in DC in 2021&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-6jace&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/6jace/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;786&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘gay growth’ isn’t happening everywhere, though. Nationwide, there has been a fall in gay bars and clubs. Famous gay bars that have been around since the beginning of the LGBTQ scene are slowly dying. Flaming Saddles in West Hollywood gone.  The Stud in San Francisco gone. Even the bar that started the fight for LGBTQ rights New York City -The Stonewall Inn- was at risk of shutting down in early 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total collected LGBTQ+ bars and clubs in 1980 by Damron’s Guide was 1,431. This year the number dropped to 1,182, according to an analysis of listings on their website. That is over a 15% decrease in the total number of LGBTQ bars nationwide. Damron’s Guide is a book that used in days before social media to find LGBTQ establishments (like how The Green Book was used in the Jim Crow era to find safe spaces for people of color).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Gay Bars/Clubs in 1980&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-4dcXz&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/4dcXz/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;445&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Gay Bars/Clubs 2021&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-b5vxf&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/b5vxf/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;445&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty states have gained LGBTQ bars since 1980, 5 have stayed at the same amount, while 26 have lost at least 1 LGBTQ bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Change in Gay Bars&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-EboxG&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/EboxG/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;513&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have attributed this decline in LGBTQ bars to the establishment of the ‘apps’ -Grindr, Tinder, Scruff. These apps  allow for people to meet other LGBTQ people, without having to spend $11 on a vodka cranberry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is true that since its initial creation in 2008, the app grindr has had a huge population growth of users- from 700,000 in 2010 to nearly 3 million users in 2021, according to the Digital Media Review, there has been no definite link that shows these apps are the reason for the ‘gay bars’ downfall. Especially since there have always been ways of meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others, like Garrett Quinby, a gay man, 28, has attributed the reduction to less of a need for ‘gay safe’ spaces in a modern, more progressive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Its about feeling safer in more spaces. They’re not as much of a need,” Quinby said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Pissourious, 27,  who is also a gay man also felt that the numbers represented a general lessened need for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think the reason is not dwindling popularity, but it feels as if it’s not as needed right now,” Pissourious said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others in the community, like Jo and Rach, believe that a mix of factors has contributed to the decline of these safe spaces. From the lack of financial security and lack of ability to pay for these spaces by those who need LGBTQ spaces the most, like younger LGBTQ individuals, and a toxic culture that has emerged since the Obergefell v. Hodges from those who feel that their fight is over, its convoluted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re like losing kindness. We’re losing a sense of community and there’s still a great amount of it. But squeaky wheels get the grease so bitchy gays get the attention and build the culture.” McDaniel said. “You can’t succeed when you exclude.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Marriage Equality Act passed and the privileged queers, whether that be white, male, cis; Kind of stopped fighting because they got it. They were safe,” Pike added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disappearance of LGBTQ safe spaces, some in the community argue, is just the beginning of a greater trend. This year, the most anti-trans legislation has been passed, ever. 17 anti-LGBTQ legislations has been enacted this year while over 10 more anti-LGBTQ bills sit on governors’ desks, according to records from the Human Rights Campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, hate crime data from the FBI has showed an increase in offences for being LGBTQ. There was a rise of 11.5% more hate crimes motivated by sexual or gender identity. The safety that the LGBTQ community gets in their LGBTQ community bars has not disappeared- it is still very needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flourish-embed flourish-chart&quot; data-src=&quot;visualisation/8053612&quot;&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some promising signs of change, though.  Washington DC’s thriving LGBTQ nightlife scene is an example of when people invest their money back into their communities, they can help. From supporting the queer owned bed and breakfast a town over, or just actively avoiding giving places that don’t support all within the community- it is possible to continue having impactful safe spaces for the LGBTQ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked about the time that made them realize that they were doing their right path, Pike beamed as McDaniel looked at them smiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ll never not work in this industry this way. Like I have way too much ability to impact the safety of humans that are in need -That are my people .”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/IMG_8916.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:42:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/gay-bars-closing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/gay-bars-closing/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blurred Lines when it comes to musical ownership</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When the Grammys announced the nominees on November 23, many in the music industry raised their eyebrows to see Taylor Swift and Jack Antonoff among those nominated for album of the year: not just for their album “Evermore”, but also for co-writing Olivia Rodrigo’s “Sour.” Considering that neither Swift nor Antonoff or Annie Clark (who’s collaborated with Swift in the past and is also nominated for “Sour”) actively wrote any Rodrigo’s “Sour”, many were perplexed by the Academy’s nod to Swift and her collaborators. On Sunday night the Recording Academy, the entity responsible for the Grammy awards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/music/awards/taylor-swift-olivia-rodrigo-grammy-2022-nomination-adjustment-1235005995/&quot;&gt;rectified the mistake&lt;/a&gt;, citing a mistake in paperwork. The Recording Academy’s confusion is yet another chapter in a long story about the difference between copyright infringement and paying proper homage to the artistic influences that came before. According to analysis of case data, musical copyright cases have been increasing in frequency over the past decade with significant increases in the past five years, raising increasing complex questions about musical ownership in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Rodrigo, the controversy over her alleged theft culminated in September, when she &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/benhenry/olivia-rodrigo-paramore-good-4-u-taylor-swift-deja-vu&quot;&gt;made headlines by giving up millions in royalties&lt;/a&gt; through granting retroactive songwriting credit to Taylor Swift for her song “déjà vu”. Rodrigo announced the additional credits after months of speculation online and a couple of a little too YouTube perfect mashups caused by many fans to point out that “déjà vu” bore a strong resemblance to Swift’s “Cruel Summer”, accusing the singer of artistic theft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some applauded Rodrigo’s move (one Tik-Toker even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@luxxuryxx/video/7000462584503667973?referer_url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.dazeddigital.com%2F&amp;amp;referer_video_id=7000462584503667973&amp;amp;refer=embed&amp;amp;is_copy_url=1&amp;amp;is_from_webapp=v1&quot;&gt;encouraged his followers to “keep narking”&lt;/a&gt;, many musical experts raised concerns on Rodrigo’s crediting artists who had no active part of the songwriting process as ‘songwriters’. Some wondered if Rodrigo’s acknowledgment that Taylor Swift was one of her largest musical influences in multiple interviews was just as responsible for the accusations of stealing as the actual musical similarities.
This idea of influence seems to be the true catch in the case of Rodrigo’s transgressions. Reporting on Rodrigo’s use of yelling vocals in the Bridge of “déjà vu” (similar vocals in Swift’s “Cruel Summer”) is almost always mentioned in connection with Rodrigo’s admittance in an interview that Swift was one of her greatest influences and inspirations. As Adam Neely, a bassist and YouTube music educator &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qX7a2p5_JsM&amp;amp;t=376s&quot;&gt;put it in his video on the Rodrigo controversy&lt;/a&gt;: “… Olivia Rodrigo was wearing her influence on her sleeve just a little too brightly for some folks.”  This strategy, of using artists’ own admittance of influence as evidence for musical theft, is eerily similar to one employed by the Gaye family in 2015 in the infamous court case surrounding Pharrell Williams and Robin Thicke’s song “Blurred Lines”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;musical-copyright-in-the-courts&quot;&gt;Musical Copyright in the Courts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015 the Gaye estate won their copyright case against Williams and Thicke for infringement on Marvin Gaye’s 1977 song “Got to Give it Up”. The Gaye Estate’s complaint dedicates several pages to Thicke’s long proclaimed admiration of Gaye’s, citing his homage to the R&amp;amp;B legend as the introductory evidence that the artist could’ve committed copyright infringement. The Gaye estate then specifically claimed that the 2013 hit “Blurred Lines” copied &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.law.gwu.edu/mcir/case/pharrell-williams-et-al-v-frankie-gaye-et-al/&quot;&gt;“signature phrase, vocal hook, backup…”&lt;/a&gt; from Marvin Gaye’s original.
The big hitch with that complaint? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/pro/features/music-copyright-lawsuits-chilling-effect-935310/&quot;&gt;Until that point&lt;/a&gt;, such secondary musical elements (i.e., elements other than melody, harmony, and rhythm) were not subject to copyright. When the Gaye’s won their case in 2015 (although appeals would last till 2018), they essentially won in copywriting a musical vibe, rather than just a specific melody or musical element. Previously, musical copyright protected what was understood to be ideas in artistic expression, not the expression themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Peter Jaszi, Professor Emeritus at American University College of Law, explained, “The standard line on that is that copyright in music…doesn’t protect the style. Anyone can try to write like Hemmingway and even if they’re very successful the Hemmingway estate doesn’t have any basis on which to sue them as long as they use their own dialogue and their own characters ….” The “Blurred Lines” case pushed against that limitation, claiming that there was more to music than just the core melodies. The 2015 court case ushered in an era of fear into the music industry as labels suddenly began to question what exactly would send them to court while the outcome in court was ultimately much harder to predict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music industry has been on edge ever since “Blurred Lines”, concerned that the affirmative ruling for the plaintiffs will set a new precedent for copyright infringement in the courts. However, according to an analysis of data compiled from GW Law School’s Musical Copyright Resource, the concerns seem to be largely unfounded, at least as far as the courts are concerned. However, it’s the reaction of the public which seems to be most intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the Blurred Lines case, the average number of cases between 2010-2015 was four cases a year. After the court decision in 2015, the average number of cases between 2016-2021 increased to 13,  more than tripling previous years’ average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Number of US Copyright Cases Brought to Court Over Last Century   (Copy)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-U6zwy&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/U6zwy/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to necessarily claim correlation but, notably, the extreme spike falls almost exactly on the date that “Blurred Lines” went to court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Cronin, Project Director of the GW Law Schools Musical Copyright Resource who began the project in the 1980s, believes this uptick is the result of ploys for cash by musicians and lawyers alike. “And these… plaintiffs typically, are represented by attorneys who are working on a contingency fee basis, which means they will get a… portion of any settlement or award, that results from the ultimate disposition of the case. And this raises, I think, the very strong possibility, if not probability, that many of these cases are brought as simply a means of shaking down a successful defendant to get a handout to get them to go away,” Cronin said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the ways courts have decided in recent years Cronin’s suspicion may not be unfounded, at least initially. In 2016, 45% percent of the cases put before the court were settled between the plaintiffs and defendants, often for undisclosed amounts of money. That’s opposed to less than one percent in 2015. Led Zeppelin and Katy Perry’s respective wins in appeals this year have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/24/arts/music/blurred-lines-led-zeppelin-copyright.html&quot;&gt;many breathing a sigh of relief&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s yet to be seen if cases will ever return to previous levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jaszi discussed this uptick he said, “I cannot prove this but I suspect that the uptick in filings that you observed is a function of that shared belief that… “Blurred Lines” was going to be the beginning of a new dispensation on music copyright. Of course, it wasn’t.” That’s the thing, “Blurred Lines” doesn’t look to have changed the way courts decide things very much at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Complaining genres post Blurred Lines&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive area chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-uN4dP&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/uN4dP/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as which genres are taken to court “Blurred Lines” again doesn’t seem to have any clear consequences. The fluctuations don’t seem to follow any patterns surrounding “Blurred Lines” except to spike after the decision, which is most likely just a result of the increase in cases. There is a spike again in 2020, when case filings rose, perhaps in reaction to a jury decision against Katy Perry (challenged by Christian rapper Flame for her song “Dark Horse”) but which was overturned in an appeals court earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fears of many music industry experts and copyright lawyers, courts haven’t seemed to give any more credence to flimsy court cases than before. As far as court decisions are concerned, as Cronin says, “The outcome of the “Blurred Lines” case is considered an outlying travesty, corrected by Zeppelin which followed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the number of cases has largely remained inflated, courts have continued to dismiss cases outright even more frequently than they grant Summary Judgments. After settlements, court dismissals (marked as Court Decisions in the graph) made up the largest portion of decisions. This should be a comfort to many who feared that “Blurred Lines” marked a new philosophy in musical copyright law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Court Decisions by Year&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-0O3PK&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/0O3PK/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;374&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the most significant change in final rulings was the number of settlements. Overall, the average number of settlements over five-year periods increased 700% after “Blurred Lines”. That data only includes cases that went to court, it doesn’t account for artists who preemptively settled before anyone ever filed. Granted, settlements are sometimes speculatively more indicative of artists granting plaintiff’s rightful credit without having their names dragged through the court, but the significance in this increase still could raise eyebrows. The number of settlements has also fallen significantly in the past two years returning to almost pre-“Blurred Lines” levels, which is undoubtedly reassuring to artists and record companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing of note is that two of the three cases decided in the past five years, including “Blurred Lines”, were for the plaintiff and contrary to what a lot of musical experts find appropriate. While one of those cases was then overturned by a judge in 2020, this trend has led many in the industry to wonder if a ‘jury of one’s peers’ truly is the best people to decide matters of musical copyright. A 2019 &lt;a href=&quot;https://variety.com/2019/biz/news/katy-perry-dark-horse-lawsuit-joyful-noise-chilling-effect-on-songwriting-1203292606/&quot;&gt;Variety&lt;/a&gt; article reports that some experts were concerned that judges and juries simply didn’t have the expertise to decide cases in musical copyright and should go before expert panels rather than a jury of one’s peers. Musical and legal experts alike have pointed out how juries are not infallible to misleading testimonies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0ytoUuO-qvg&quot;&gt;Youtube video on the Katy Perry jury decision&lt;/a&gt;,  Adam Neely addresses Todd Decker, the plaintiff’s expert on the “Dark Horse” case, directly: “I sincerely doubt you would make the arguments that you made in court at an academic conference… because your academic peers would absolutely eviscerate you for saying some of those things. And yet, in front of a jury of your peers, you told them. These are non-experts, these aren’t musicians and they were confused by your jargon…” It points like Neely’s that have led to conclusions like the ones expressed by experts in Variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jaszi disagrees with such arguments, “I’m static in the sense that I think that jurors are easily swayed. I’m critical in the sense that it is the role of lawyers to try to counteract that effect. And I’m unpersuaded that music presents a special case of what is really a general phenomenon in copyright law.” Essentially, it is up to the lawyers to argue their cases well, not for jury members to be experts on musical theory and copyright law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judith Finell, a musicologist who advises companies like HBO and served as the expert witness for the Gaye foundation in “Blurred Lines”, is also skeptical about removing juries from musical copyright, “It’s really the job of the attorneys and the experts to make it clear enough to the people that they can make a reasonable decision…. It can’t just be in the opinion of one of the musicians, it really has to be perceived by other human beings who are in a position to say guilty or not guilty, just like any other form of crime, right? It’s a form of theft. But if you can only prove that something was taken.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given recent court decisions, it seems that calls for expert panels in place of juries may be prematurely reactive. The Katy Perry jury decision was vacated in an appeals court this year and the Led Zeppelin jury decided in the defendant’s favor, not allowing the plaintiffs to claim copyright over the chord progressions and melody many associates with “Stairway to Heaven.”  Finally, as the data in this article indicates, very few cases ever go in front of juries, to begin with, seeming to indicate that the courts themselves haven’t significantly changed their attitude towards copyright in the wake of “Blurred Lines.” 
##Beyond the Courts 
While “Blurred Lines” seems to be an outlier rather than a new precedent in the courts,  its effects are felt in ways that weren’t documented in court filings. With amateurs being able to flood the internet with their accusations of copyright infringement, artists are increasingly under scrutiny for their music and whether or not it is paying proper credit to the Fcreators that preceded it. Artists are losing credence over their artistic expression and the money they earned, just to avoid a court case. And artists aren’t the only ones losing out, music fans are too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/pro/features/music-copyright-lawsuits-chilling-effect-935310/&quot;&gt;According to a report from Rolling Stone&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year, musicologists are increasingly employed by musicians in attempts to avoid copyright lawsuits. Essentially, musicologists are advising artists on how to make their songs distinct enough to avoid copyright infringement. This practice may be a useful legal tool, but it brings up questions about artistic expression. No artistic creation was created in a vacuum. It’s the nature of all art that it’s influenced or inspired by the creations that proceed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world where similarities and influences are just time bombs for court cases, new songs could be getting crushed under this bizarre form of self-censorship, tucked away for similarities that may not legally be significant. Artists are thereby shouldering not only creative responsibilities in the recording room but legal ones as well. “It strikes me as writing music with a musicologist and a lawyer in the room, that’s a lot of that’s a lot of weight for an artist to carry….” Jaszi said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finnel, who works with companies from Disney on CBS advising on this very subject, acknowledges that this fear might be a real one, but believes that if musicologists are doing their job, it shouldn’t be too large a problem, at least not legally. “… that [creative instincts being stymied] could happen if you were to advise artists not to write like anyone else in the same style. But if you’re actually just advising artists, not to cut, not to lift exact music that’s deliberately imitating someone else’s music, then that would be sort of the best approach that takes judgment and knowledge.” Hopefully, musicologists should know their craft better than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accusations of copying are now coming from fans rather than artists, as perfect mashups and similar note progressions, “vibes of songs” which are not subject to copyright, are confused for stealing. However, Cronin doesn’t think that such public-sourced outcry will necessarily translate to court action,  “I don’t think courts take that into account much, they’re not supposed to. Nevertheless, it may affect the parties that are bringing the suit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finell too, was doubtful about public discourse affecting the courts, “… Usually, when I read online opinions, by perhaps non-musicians, or non-musicologist, some of the similarities that people pick up….There’s a lot of misunderstanding and misconceptions about what matters in music when it comes to copyright-protected action. And so sometimes it’s only stylistic, and it’s just nothing concrete.” Legally, then, the public masses may not be the greatest threat to artistic freedom but it certainly begins to bring up the important question of how to properly acknowledge and at times offer monetary credit to influences, especially as fan culture increasingly becomes a loyalist one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line between when to acknowledge the artistic influence and when to give monetary credit can be a difficult one to draw. And it may be beyond the scope of the courts to say. Jaszi put it this way: “… If the effect of this sort of consciousness-raising, or to cause people to behave more, or honestly a generous way. That would be, that would be great. But it wouldn’t be law, it would be a change in practice.” In that, Jaszi is correct. The trick now is navigating the court of public opinion and convincing fans that proper credit has been given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while courts have withstood the onslaught, claims presumably filed under the hope that  “Blurred Lines” changed the way courts treated musical copyright. However, the questions it raised about influence and credit are still circulating in the public sphere. In a world where artists admitting admiration for other artists is used as fodder for allegations of theft, artists may err on the side of caution and not speak openly of their influences and thereby deny proper credit to those who came before them. There needs to be space for fair deference to influence without legal ramifications in the art world because without it, who knows what artists and songs could be buried under the fears of copyright lawsuits or public derision. The only question is whether the court of public opinion will allow it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/blurred-lines-music-lawsuits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/blurred-lines-music-lawsuits/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Women are paying more than men for similar products, and states are reaping the benefits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine you head into the store, going straight to the women’s section to buy a new pair of dress pants for your upcoming job interview. You’re in desperate need of high-quality, professional slacks, but can’t afford to spend an unlimited amount. The cheapest pair you can find is $119. You reason with yourself that they’re worth the cost and head to the register to check out. As your cashier says, “That’ll be $119,” the person next to you, buying the same pair of dress pants, yet from the men’s section, is only being charged $98. You frown and wonder how you’re possibly paying more than them, but sigh and reluctantly slide your card into the machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-from-2021&quot;&gt;Data from 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, women pay more than men for the same products. Ranging from baby clothes and children’s toys to adult clothing to senior care items and medications, products designed for women are, on average, more expensive than those geared towards men. Based on a 2015 study conducted by the New York City Department of Consumer Affairs, “women’s products cost 7 percent more than similar products for men.” Since 2015, prices have increased for women’s clothing and toiletries but decreased for children’s clothing and toys and senior care items geared towards girls and women. From data collected in 2021, on average, adult clothing is $4.61 more expensive for women, and women’s toiletries cost $1.15 more than men’s. Children’s items cost $0.29 less for girls and senior care items and medicine for women has decreased in price by $0.43.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Difference in Price for Adult Clothing, Children's Clothing/Toys, Toiletries, and Senior Care Items in 2021&quot; aria-label=&quot;Grouped Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-t4zFG&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/t4zFG/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;479&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-from-2015&quot;&gt;Data from 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York City Department of Consumer Affairs determined that in 2015, for children’s clothes and toys, products for girls were $1.45 more on average than those for boys. Additionally, on average, adult women paid $2.91 more for clothing, while women also paid $0.07 more for toiletries and $1.98 more for senior care items and medications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Women are paying thousands of dollars more over the course of their lives to purchase similar products as men,” states the 2015 report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, the term “women” and products “geared towards women” are defined as those that an individual who identifies as female would purchase, not necessarily only for those who were assigned female at birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Difference in Price for Adult Clothing, Children's Clothing/Toys, Toiletries, and Senior Care Items in 2015&quot; aria-label=&quot;Grouped Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-bT51O&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/bT51O/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;479&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the price gap is not necessarily just individual preference and societal standards of genders. The price gap comes from a structured system invisible to the ordinary consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structures-and-substitution&quot;&gt;Structures and substitution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[C]hoices made by manufacturers and retailers result in a greater financial burden for female consumers than for male consumers,” reports the New York City Department of Consumer Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, it is not the manufacturer or retail companies that take on the responsibility of this higher price. Instead, it is the average American consumer that is forced to pay this greater number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The burden is on the female consumer as it is on women in a wide variety of issues,” says Anna Bessendorf, the author of the New York Consumer Affairs Project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www1.nyc.gov/assets/dca/downloads/pdf/partners/Study-of-Gender-Pricing-in-NYC.pdf&quot;&gt;“From Cradle to Cane: The Cost of Being a Female Consumer.”&lt;/a&gt; This type of “pink tax” is still undertaken by the ordinary American consumer, resulting in a financial burden for a large portion of the United States population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the cause of gender pricing, knowledge of product substitution is essential. Overall, women’s products have fewer substitutes than men’s, meaning that they have fewer options if a brand changes the product or its size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because women are more insensitive to a price change because they don’t have close substitutes, we might expect the prices to be higher for many women’s clothing items and anything that fits that pattern,” says Mary Hansen, a professor of economics at American University in Washington, D.C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without close substitutes, female consumers are forced to change brands or sizes and typically spend more money to have access to products that fit their body type and appeal to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you are a consumer woman and you went to X brand and you know that those jeans and that shirt fit you, probably next season somebody somewhere decided to change the cut, which usually meant you had to change your size,” says Renee Villandry, a past retail manager at Banana Republic and Loft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female consumers are then faced with the added burden of finding new brands and sizes that work for them, as well as the higher prices. “You only get price equality when stuff is perfectly substitutable for each other,” states Hansen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;population-differences&quot;&gt;Population differences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, since the initial study was conducted in New York City, it is crucial to study the gender breakdown of one of the most densely populated areas in the nation. Using data from the U.S. Census, it was found that New York City has a slightly higher percentage of women than the national average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Percentage of US and NYC Population by Gender in 2019&quot; aria-label=&quot;Grouped Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-ZccM7&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ZccM7/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;313&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the national level, women make up 50.8% of the population. New York City has 1.5% more women than the national average, with a population of 4.3 million total women, making it so the higher average prices of necessary items inflict a large burden on the majority of those who live in the largest metropolitan area of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With just over half of the U.S. population identifying as female and as consumers for these women-geared products, there is a significant financial burden that over half the population takes on. This pricing issue, therefore, affects a multitude of individuals, not just a small group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pay-gaps&quot;&gt;Pay gaps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it is crucial to look at the payment gaps between men and women in New York City and the entire United States. New York City comprises 10 congressional districts, which are diagrammed below by combining them into New York City’s five boroughs, displaying the pay gap of men’s and women’s median earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Pay Gap in New York City for Median Earnings&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-75XUY&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/75XUY/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;766&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In every congressional district except for three, women earn substantially less than men, averaging a pay gap of $5,273 per year, yet is below both the state and national average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New York state averages a pay gap of $8,541 based on data from the Joint Economic Committee from the United States Congress. The map below depicts the pay gaps by congressional districts of the entire state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Pay Gap in New York by Congressional District for Men's and Women's Median Earnings&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-8oU8q&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/8oU8q/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;611&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparatively, New York City averages a smaller pay gap, with three congressional districts where women earn on average more than men. However, in districts outside the city, the pay gap increases far beyond the state and national averages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the United States as a whole, women’s median earnings average $9,955 per year less than men, yet they still pay higher prices for similar goods as depicted above. Pay gaps vary across states, as seen below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Pay Gap by Median Earnings for Men and Women by State&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-SOkLA&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/SOkLA/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;503&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the nation, women are affected by pay gaps and higher prices. In every state, on average, women earn less than men, which greatly impacts the quality of life women can live. Yet, states reap the most benefits from the higher prices women face, especially from the taxes imposed on menstrual products, which are necessary to a menstruating consumer’s livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pink-tax&quot;&gt;The pink tax&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Period Equity, a legal organization dedicated to achieving menstruation equity, only 23 of the 50 U.S. states do not impose a tax on menstrual products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;States and &amp;quot;Pink Tax&amp;quot; Status &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-ei5Q9&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ei5Q9/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;469&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than half the country imposing taxes on products necessary for a menstruator’s natural bodily function, people who menstruate are facing the financial burden that states monetarily benefit from. This tax garners thousands of dollars for the states and takes away crucial funds from menstruators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Total State Revenue from &amp;quot;Pink Tax&amp;quot; Per Capita (in billions)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-HPBZQ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/HPBZQ/3/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;483&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, states are taking vital funds away from those that need it most. Additionally, in states like North Dakota and Wyoming, pay gaps are higher and states are making more money from the pink tax, taking more funds from menstruators who already face a lower income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In areas like these, those who menstruate and/or identify as women are faced with the highest financial burden. Higher flat prices of products geared towards women and taxes imposed on necessary items for menstruators creates a consequential effect on the women’s and menstruators’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The best thing that women can really do is have awareness and choose alternatives when they’re available,” offers Bessendorf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;change-across-the-nation&quot;&gt;Change across the nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economics, taxes, and price points govern much of an American’s life and societal values. With the data found and reported on, women are paying more than men for similar products, and states are gaining substantial revenue for this process. Those who identify as women and menstruators then face the monetary effects of these actions throughout their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, change is currently and constantly taking place across the country. In 2021 alone, Louisiana and Vermont have eliminated the pink tax and 36 pieces of legislation have been introduced in other state legislatures aimed at removing this tax, four of which are still in session, according to Period Equity. Prices on average for children’s clothing and toys geared towards girls’ and women’s senior care items have also dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If parents are buying the same toys for their boys and girls, that means the toys are increasingly substitutes and that’s exactly…the kind of place where you would see minimal price differences between target markets,” remarks Hansen, providing economic insight to the growing movement for unisex baby and children’s items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more individuals choosing to consume beyond the binary lines, therefore avoiding gender-based price barriers, society is evolving to know an economy without these implementations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social movements and societal acceptance of loosening the binary on consumer goods help lessen the burden of substitution on women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To the extent that social trends lead to previously gendered products really being substitutes for large portions of the population,” Hansen states, “you’re not going to see those [price] differences.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By moving away from gender-based products and reducing the binary labels throughout society, we look towards a more equitable, inclusive consumer future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/pink-tax/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/pink-tax/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The World’s Largest MLM has Given Millions to Republicans to Restrict the Rights of Their Sellers</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Pain is temporary, but your dreams are going to last forever if you let them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is Adrian Mitchell’s self-described credo that he aspires to live by for the rest of his life; however, just two years ago, this was the furthest thing from his mind. After silently struggling with his mental health throughout his youth, Adrian decided to drop out of college in 2018 and seek professional help. Although things were somewhat better after seeing a psychologist and returning home, Adrian’s life took another twist when he was diagnosed with MS. “I just kept fighting in the hopes that I could reach out and grab that light at the end of the tunnel,” Adrian said. But he didn’t grab the light. One day as he was scrolling through Instagram, a friend from college direct messaged Adrian with a proposal that he says, “saved my life.” Adrian had received an offer to join Monat, a billion-dollar shampoo and wellness company, as a “Market Partner.” With the promise of “being his own boss” and “living life on his own terms,” all Adrian had to do was pay $200 recruitment fee and he would receive personalized training, a variety of company products, and a fresh start. The light grabbed him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-dream-with-some-strings-attached&quot;&gt;A Dream With Some Strings Attached&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monat is a Multi-level Marketing (MLM) company, a type of business that is primarily predicated on independent sellers who sell product and recruit more sellers. While Monat’s social media account and website present the vouge-like appearance and lavish looking products one would come to expect of a modern beauty company, their business model could not be more different. With &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dsa.org/statistics-insights/factsheets&quot;&gt;billions of dollars in sales&lt;/a&gt; across the US, powerful MLMs like Monat wield an incredible amount of power over their sellers and the governmental regulations that they abide by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Adrian believes that he has had a “personal rebirth” due to his newfound purpose and community he developed throughout his year-long tenure selling for Monat, his experience is  not reflective of all newly initiated Market Partners. Gemma Miller, an ex-seller for Monat, talked with me about her vastly differing experience working for Monat. “They didn’t treat me like I was even human,” Gemma recounted as she looked back upon her time within the company. Gemma estimates that she lost thousands of dollars selling for Monat because of the “constant pressure from leadership” to buy more products to advertise on her social media. Furthermore, Gemma described the social isolation she felt after having tried to “rope everyone I knew” into the business just as her uplines had told her to do. Compared to the typical door-knocking MLM selling of the past, Monat’s business is conducted exclusively through social media, with their sellers posing as quasi-influencers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although MLMs have different internal structures, they all share a rank system by which sellers can “rank-up” to different tiers by achieving a targeted goal of sales and recruits. While MLMs have often been compared to pyramid schemes due to the high monetary incentive to recruit others, they are currently legal under US law and were reported to have made upwards of $40 billion in sales &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dsa.org/statistics-insights/factsheets&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;. However, the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) nonetheless harshly advises against joining an MLM due to their financially disparate results. A study conducted by the FTC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/documents/public_comments/trade-regulation-rule-disclosure-requirements-and-prohibitions-concerning-business-opportunities-ftc.r511993-00008%C2%A0/00008-57281.pdf.&quot;&gt;analyzed&lt;/a&gt; the income breakdowns of more than 30 MLMs and found that nearly 99.6% of sellers in an MLM lose money. Although masses of publicly available studies that share similar findings should reasonably ward off anyone from joining an MLM, the Direct Selling Association (DSA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dsa.org/statistics-insights/factsheets&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that there are nearly 8 million “direct sellers” currently operating in the US. While the DSA operates on behalf of almost all prominent MLMs, their privately collected data should not be readily ignored. Because most MLMs keep their financial data relatively close to their chest, it is difficult to accurately quantify their business operations. However, Amway, which brought in $8.5 billion in revenue in 2020 and is often credited as the world’s largest MLM, has droves of publicly available data from a surprisingly obvious source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1990, Amway has made over $20 million dollars in political donations to politicians and campaigns through their holding company, Alticor. Because all political donations are legally required to be accessible by the public, every recipient of Alticor’s donations can be viewed on the Federal Elections Committee’s (FEC) website. Due to a lack of any internal data from prominent MLMs, their political donations and lobbied bills can glean some insight as to what governmental changes they wish to see in relation to sellers like Adrian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;amway-and-the-republican-party&quot;&gt;Amway and the Republican Party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amway has heavily supported the Republican party according to an analysis of two decades worth of political donations. More specifically, over 99% of their political donations have gone towards Republican campaigns and advocacy groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Alticor/Amway Donations Since 2012&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-nhfNV&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nhfNV/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;360&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow=e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not a new revelation. Alticor’s relationship with the Republican party has been strong for almost two decades. One month before the November 1994 elections, Alticor donated nearly $2.5 million dollars to the GOP, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.motherjones.com/politics/1996/09/she-did-it-amway/&quot;&gt;largest political donation in history&lt;/a&gt; for a single election at one time. Following the GOP sweep in 1994, Amway co-founder Richard DeVos was personally honored by future Senate President and Republican Nominee Bob Dole at a lavish fundraising event. Since 2012, Alticor’s top recipient of funds has been the Republican National Committee, followed by other Republican and conservative-leaning groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Top 5 Recipients of Alitcor Donations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Column Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-cclOQ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/cclOQ/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;315&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the massive amount of money poured into national Republican groups, Alticor has donated nearly $850,000 to the Michigan Republican Party, the state where their headquarters reside. Not including the massive contribution to Dick DeVos’ bid for the governor of Michigan, the DeVos personal donations also align quite heavily with that of Alticor as well, marking another visible trend in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;DeVos Family Donations Since 1996&quot; aria-label=&quot;Pie Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-lH0Nf&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/lH0Nf/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;582&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following their largest year of political spending in 2016, Betsey DeVos, daughter-in-law of Richard DeVos and husband of former Amway president Dick DeVos, was nominated by President Trump to serve as his Secretary of Education. While it is obvious that there is a link between the most powerful MLM and the Republican party, following money trail can give insight as to why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-money-trail&quot;&gt;The Money Trail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to their political donations, Alticor also engages in a substantial amount of lobbying every year. By looking at the specific bills that Alticor has put hundreds of thousands of dollars towards, some insight can be gained as to how they view their employees and products. Edgar Vasquez, an analyst for the lobbying firm Invariant told me “Companies like Alticor often hire people like us to act as ‘middlemen’ with lawmakers” to advocate on behalf of policies that they see as being advantageous. Spending roughly $500,000 dollars a year on lobbying, Alticor has continually pushed legislation to deem their sellers as “independent contractors” as opposed to employees. Recently, Alticor lobbied the &lt;em&gt;New GIG Act of 2019&lt;/em&gt;, alongside other companies such as Uber and Lyft. Introduced by Congressman Tom Rice, a recipient of Alticor money, the &lt;em&gt;NEW Gig Act of 2019&lt;/em&gt;, produces a legal statute that would restrict millions of employees from gaining many benefits were they to be labeled as independent contractors. Because the Affordable Care Act (ACA) imposes a hefty penalty on businesses over fifty employees that do not provide healthcare to at least 95% their employees, the nomenclature change to “independent contractor” subverts this fine. Additionally, independent contractors are not included within minimum wage requirements, federal discrimination laws, and labor regulations, leaving them with virtually no government protection. While an argument can be made that MLM sellers should classify as independent contractors, the protections that this status affords them severely limits their financial options. Although sellers should do their due diligence regarding their employers, vulnerable individuals can fall prey to these companies with little recourse should they fall into the 99% of people who lose money within an MLM. Adrian, who continues to struggle with his mental health and MS, is about to turn twenty-six, the age when he is no longer eligible to be covered under his mother’s health insurance. While Alticor and other prominent MLMs lobby millions of dollars to label their employees as independent contractors, Adrian is trying to find a way to pay for his future medical bills without the help of his employer. Because the Republican party has so often declared itself as the “party of small government” and resented intrusive business regulation, the lack of protections for independent contractors within MLMs makes it nearly impossible for struggling sellers to “pull themselves up by their bootstraps.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although numerous Congressmembers have received donations from Alticor, there are currently thirteen house members and twelve senators in Congress that have both received money from Alticor and introduced a bill that the MLM has lobbied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Current Congressional Members Supported by Alticor*&quot; aria-label=&quot;Table&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-UxOOs&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/UxOOs/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;878&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some could write off these donations as being purely coincidental, Tim Walberg and Marsha Blackburn stand out as being the top two recipients of Alticor money. Unsurprisingly, both members played a role in the Congressional Direct Selling Caucus, a group of Congressmembers who advocate on behalf of MLM sellers and executives. Blackburn, the founder of the caucus has since left due to her election to the Senate, while Walberg continues to serve in the coalition. Amway wields a tremendous amount of power as the world’s largest MLM, and it is the duty of consumers, sellers, and politicians to recognize these schemes and curb their influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;persevering-through-the-pain&quot;&gt;Persevering Through the Pain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the Republican and Democrat parties have been ideologically separated for decades regarding the proper extent of business regulations, the unchecked power and overwhelmingly harmful impacts of MLMs should be a sign to Republicans that their tactics are not working. But partisan bickering means nothing to sellers like Adrian. When asked about the future medical expenses that he will have to pay without the help of his employers, Adrian once again repeated his moto. “Pain is temporary, but your dreams are going to last forever if you let them.” While he is still at the first rank of Monat, Adrian nonetheless pursues his dream of helping others, hoping that his pain is indeed temporary.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:39:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/mlm-alticor-lobbying/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/mlm-alticor-lobbying/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Pandemic Mental Health Crisis: How the world is healing after a year of struggle</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mental-health-what-happened&quot;&gt;Mental Health: What happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost 20 months of the Coronavirus pandemic ravaging through the United States, the long term effects of isolation have become abundantly clear–particularly as people strive to achieve a sense of “normalcy.” Though the global health effects have long been discussed, the individual, less-publicized effects are equally worth studying, particularly when they can cause damage in one’s body, and their mind.
As the Covid-19 pandemic took over the United States, consuming our lives, so did mental health issues. More specifically, anxiety and depression–two of the most common mental illnesses in the US (&lt;em&gt;National Institute of Mental Health&lt;/em&gt;). Studies about these disorders can enlighten us when it comes to the impact that the pandemic has had on mental health. In a study by the &lt;strong&gt;National Center for Health Statistics&lt;/strong&gt; symptoms were quantified using a scale, and measured over the course of 7-days by adults all around the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Symptoms of Anxiety and Depression Throughout 2020 &quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-A4In3&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/A4In3/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anxiety-and-depression&quot;&gt;Anxiety and Depression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, the month with the &lt;strong&gt;highest percentage of anxiety and depression symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; during the year of 2020 was &lt;strong&gt;December.&lt;/strong&gt; This aligns with the start of an upward trend in Covid cases and hospitalizations during the month, which led to stricter regulations and an increased lockdown. In fact, as the year went on, mental health fluctuated very much in conjunction with the amount of covid cases. As restrictions began to be lifted in April, there was a sharp decrease in the average number of symptoms, but as cases rose and restrictions did too, there were evident increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-collegiate-impact&quot;&gt;The collegiate impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic first hit in March of 2020 and students were sent home from schools and universities, isolation began. This was particularly difficult for college students and young adults, &lt;strong&gt;ages 18-29&lt;/strong&gt;; students were forcibly removed from their social lives, going back to living in their childhood bedrooms and having limited outside contact. As these challenges faced the country, colleges suddenly had to adapt to a growing number of mental health concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Symptoms of Mental Health by Age in 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Column Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-nPqVJ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nPqVJ/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;208&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;American University&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Washington DC,&lt;/strong&gt; the counseling center became inundated with requests for telehealth appointments, and these requests only increased as the year went on.
&lt;strong&gt;Jacqueline Darby, Director of Clinical Services at the AU Counseling Center&lt;/strong&gt; acknowledges that this pandemic has brought to light the importance of mental health awareness. “I think COVID-19 has brought to people’s attention the importance of taking care of their mental health,” she says. “COVID-19 was and still is a hard time for everyone and it makes sense that individuals need support in processing all that occurred during 2020.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the pandemic, the AU Counseling Center has seen an &lt;strong&gt;increase in counseling appointments,&lt;/strong&gt; given partially because this year, more students are able to access the counseling services. “Last year, we were limited by licensure requirements, and we could only see students who were physically located in DC, Maryland or Virginia. Now, with students being back on campus more people can use our services.” This increase in services has been a remarkable help for the AU community, largely encouraging the use of mental health resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Renee Gopon, an American University sophomore, she felt that her mental health was definitely impacted by the challenges of online school, especially at the outset of the pandemic in March. “Looking at a screen all day, on top of countless students being at home, affected students’ ability to be enthusiastic about their studies, which for me impacted my grades.” When students are faced with these challenges, it becomes harder to tend to mental health, as Gopon mentions. “There were so many factors that impacted mental health because of the pandemic and I think that the circumstances of quarantine made it difficult for anyone to thrive in an emotional mental capacity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;international-perspective&quot;&gt;International Perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For international students at American University and beyond, mental health challenges are augmented due to time differences, online classes, and simply the transition of living in a new country. Eric Rafael Torija Mosquera is from Luxembourg, and carried out his Covid-19 quarantine from his home in Europe. “As an international student, there are a lot of mental health challenges,” he says, in regards to the 2020 pandemic. “During my experience online during the lockdown of fall 2020, very little was done to accommodate the needs of internationals.”
Mosquera mentioned the late registration times for classes, lack of accommodations for time differences, and difficulty in building a sense of community. “You and your friends all have so much to do, which makes it harder to make meaningful friendships which decrease mental health,” he says, noting the importance of friendship to his own mental health. “My friends get me through any mental health challenge that comes up. If you have a community, you’re surviving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;forming-community&quot;&gt;Forming Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But international students are not the only ones who feel that a sense of belonging during tough times can improve mental health. Adam Hussaini, an AU sophomore studying Political Science, remarked that the lack of community has worsened his mental health. “I think more of an on-campus community is vital to feeling a part of something. You need to find your identity as an AU student, and with a stronger community–especially during the pandemic–this would help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an increase in workload as he moves through sophomore year, Hussaini wonders how the AU community is working to better support the student’s mental health.”Challenge Accepted is trying to have us take on challenges,” he says, “but &lt;strong&gt;how are we supposed to do that when we are already challenged with our mental health and the pandemic?&lt;/strong&gt; How are we to take on more challenges when we are set back with mental health problems?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dc-data&quot;&gt;DC Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While American University feels the weight of mental health struggles, so does the DC community at large. In terms of which mental health services were most requested over the past year, community support and therapy stay close to the top of the list. This is unsurprising, given the need for community mental health resources during a pandemic, as well as increased therapy appointments for individuals needing to discuss their unique concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;January 2021 DC Behavioral Health Report(Oct 1, 2019-Sept 30, 2020)&quot; aria-label=&quot;Bar Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-AM8cT&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/AM8cT/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;428&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to DMV native Hope Lockwood, she strongly believes that isolation, specifically back in the heart of the pandemic, is what has led to this need for greater services. “I think a lot of people have felt isolated (during the pandemic) which has caused a deterioration in overall mental health,” she says. Hope is not alone in this belief–when surveyed, AU students overwhelmingly agreed that they have felt the impacts of isolation personally, leading to an increase in anxiety and depression symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Symptoms of Anxiety and Depression in the US &quot; aria-label=&quot;Map&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-yPwtb&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/yPwtb/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;525&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, the entire US saw the impact of anxiety and depression rates climbing throughout Covid-19. Though the entire US was hit hard, &lt;strong&gt;Louisiana, Nevada, and Mississippi&lt;/strong&gt; were hit the hardest specifically by anxiety and depression symptoms. For these states particularly, mental health resources are more than necessary. For every state, though, &lt;strong&gt;a greater awareness of mental health issues is necessary&lt;/strong&gt; in order for us to thrive during these challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:38:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/mental-health-covid-19/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/mental-health-covid-19/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Health</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How green is the grass on the Friedham Quad?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;American University in Washington, D.C. was the first university in America to achieve carbon neutrality, yet this distinction has faced some questioning in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aus-sustainability-journey&quot;&gt;AU’s sustainability journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, AU joined 500 other American colleges and universities by signing onto the American College and University Presidents Climate Commitment to address the looming threat of climate change. The next year, the University created its Office of Sustainability to promote sustainable living and service, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.american.edu/about/sustainability/milestones.cfm&quot;&gt;AU’s Sustainability website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over that past 10 years, AU installed a solar hot water system, its first Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED) Certified Building, the creation of a fossil-free fund and its first sustainability plan, among other sustainability achievements, according to the Sustainability website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first sustainability plan for the University was created in 2010, as well as the Zero Waste Policy. During that same year, AU established its goal to reach carbon neutrality by 2020—a goal it reached two years prior in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Second Nature, an organization that manages the &lt;a href=&quot;https://secondnature.org/climate-action-guidance/network/&quot;&gt;Presidents’ Climate Leadership Commitments and the Climate Leadership Network&lt;/a&gt;, carbon neutrality is defined as “having no net greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;achieving-the-carbon-neutrality-title&quot;&gt;Achieving the carbon neutrality title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways in which these emissions are reduced: eliminating net GHG emissions and or the minimization of GHG emissions. This process includes purchasing “carbon offsets or other measures to mitigate the remaining emissions,” according to Second Nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these mitigation efforts is achieved through the purchase of renewable energy credits (RECs). According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/repowertoolbox/renewable-energy-certificate-monetization&quot;&gt;Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)&lt;/a&gt;, RECs are defined as “tradeable, market-based instrument(s) that represent the legal property rights to the ‘renewable-ness.” In other words, this allows AU to offset what the campus emits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process for determining emissions falls into three categories: Scope 1: emissions directly from campus, Scope 2: purchased electricity and Scope 3: indirect emissions, or everything that doesn’t fall directly into Scope 1 and 2, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.american.edu/about/sustainability/tracking-progress.cfm&quot;&gt;AU’s tracking process&lt;/a&gt;. The reduction or elimination of these categories leads to carbon neutrality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent times, this title has come under scrutiny as AU cannot physically be carbon neutral, but rather, gains its neutrality through purchasing RECs and external efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;emissions-growth-over-time&quot;&gt;Emissions growth over time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2004, the total combustion and emissions of the University rose by almost 6%. According to the EPA, the process for RECs works so that for every emission output, the buyer needs to increase the RECs to match, or buy more RECs to exceed the emission output. So, as AU increases its emissions, they also increase their purchase of RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;AU Emissions and RECs, 2004-2019&quot; aria-label=&quot;Split Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-8i5qE&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/8i5qE/4/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;445&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AU uses its carbon neutrality status in its branding, marketing and admissions campaigns. However, AU is carbon neutral on paper, rather than through physical practice. Instead of expanding and investing in on-campus resources, like solar panels, wind generation and other renewable energy methods, the University invested in a solar farm in North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-au-got-the-title&quot;&gt;How AU got the title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tacy Lambiase is the Sustainability Manager at AU’s Office of Sustainability. Among other things, she is one of many who oversee the sustainability agenda of the University and the community outreach of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data collection process to calculate the emissions includes an institutional survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We do an annual inventory every year. To collect data, we calculate faculty, staff and students’ emissions across campus. A portion of our community gets surveyed every year,” Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the Office of Institutional Research calculates the percentages needed to survey the community, as well as the estimated target response rate for the community, Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey consists of a list of questions regarding personal emissions. For example, transportation needs like commute time or plane mileage for study abroad are questions in the survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are able to get a pretty good sense of how our community is emitting, and the implications related to that,” Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become carbon neutral, the University needs to produce enough renewable energy or purchase offsets to achieve neutrality. There needs to be enough of these resources to exceed, or match, the campus carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple strategies used to achieve neutrality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The first is to reduce emissions as much as possible. The second is changing the sources of fuel on campus, like the University’s switch from steam to low temperature hot water,” Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last method of zero net emissions includes a monetary investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the third is investing in 100% renewable energy,” Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The budget for the purchases of RECs comes from the Facilities Management budget, according to Lambiase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AU has to rely on such external methods for carbon neutrality investment due to limited campus space. In other words, AU does not have the physical space to provide solar and wind resources to overcome the campus electricity and power needs, Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since AU is an urban campus and doesn’t have the space to build entire farms, they built an off-campus solar farm in &lt;a href=&quot;https://wjla.com/news/local/george-washington-university-american-university-make-deal-to-buy-solar-power-farms--104425&quot;&gt;North Carolina&lt;/a&gt;. The entire farm contains a quarter of a million solar panels, but the output of these meets only 50% of the campus electricity needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The energy that is generated by those solar panels is going to the local North Carolina grid. The energy goes to those communities…they are not directly traveling to D.C.,” Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these solar and wind farms, RECs are purchased to help offset the energy coming from D.C.’s energy grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this investment also includes on-campus renewables, such as the solar panels on 10 of AU’s rooftops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are looking to expand that,” Lambiase said. 
It’s important to note that, despite the 2,500 panels located across campus, it only covers half of a percent of the campus needs, Lambiase said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon neutrality comes from this plethora of emission resources and solutions. However, it does not allow AU to hold the most carbon-neutral school in America. AU has not claimed such a title but holds the “first large campus and the first university to become carbon neutral,” according to Second Nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes some students skeptical of AU’s sustainability commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some students are concerned with the greenwash effect. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/g/greenwashing.asp&quot;&gt;Greenwashing&lt;/a&gt; is the phenomenon or the practice of “making unwarranted or overblown claims of sustainability or environmental friendliness in an attempt to gain market share,” according to Environmental Health Perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-au-measure-up-in-the-us&quot;&gt;How does AU measure up in the U.S.?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2018, the EPA archives the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/greenpower/green-power-partnership-top-30-college-university-pdfs&quot;&gt;top 30&lt;/a&gt; carbon neutral colleges in America, on an almost quarterly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;AU ranking in Top 30 Green Schools, 2018-2021&quot; aria-label=&quot;Column Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-klc6w&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/klc6w/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the EPA, while AU is in the top 30 carbon-neutral colleges, it has never come in first place, nor the top 10. Most recently, AU ranked last in the list of top 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Ranking of Top 30 Green Colleges &amp;amp;amp; Universities in the U.S.
&quot; aria-label=&quot;Split Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-eyIrv&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/eyIrv/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;1059&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While AU has become carbon neutral, the school does not measure up to other schools in America in terms of green power usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-of-sustainability-at-au&quot;&gt;Future of sustainability at AU&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesse Cross is the University’s Zero Waste Manager. He oversees the campus recycling process and works to implement community outreach. He’s witnessed the evolution of campus sustainability as a student and now a staff member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There was a really big push around 2018…with the three bins,” Cross said in an interview. “We work with a partner facility, Prince George’s County Composting Facility, for composting. We can’t send any contaminates,” Cross said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where student volunteers, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.american.edu/about/sustainability/get-involved/ecorep-program.cfm&quot;&gt;EcoReps&lt;/a&gt;, come in. One job of the volunteers is to check and sort bags for possible contaminants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking past the last few years, AU has plans to become completely zero waste by 2030—a step that requires “all work on all ends,” Cross said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimi Beckemeier is an Environmental Studies and Computer Science major, and volunteers at the Office of Sustainability as an EcoRep. Her line of work includes sustainable volunteering, working with 4Ocean, and updating her sustainability blog with resources for the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“AU is doing a good job of improving… sustainable living, however, there is always room for improvement. There is a plan in the works for this already, but the biggest thing I would say is to get rid of single-use plastics in our dining halls,” Beckemeier said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usnews.com/education/best-colleges/articles/how-many-universities-are-in-the-us-and-why-that-number-is-changing&quot;&gt;U.S. News&lt;/a&gt;, there are 3,982 colleges in America. By looking at AU’s commitment to environmental sustainability, they rank higher than the majority of colleges and universities in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to the environment can be seen in a variety of environmental science and sustainability programs as well as clubs, and even in the Office of Sustainability. To that end, many students also share this commitment to greater environmental justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aside from individual actions such as eating less meat, thrifting…there is an abundance of programs, resources and people willing to help students turn sustainable,” Beckemeier said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beckemeier acknowledges that while AU has employed many tactics in overcoming carbon emissions, there are areas that could use improvements, such as plastic-free lunches, farmers’ markets and outdoor events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It looks like more environmental organizations, environmental legislation, and more environmental education,” Beckemeier said.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/green-campus-au/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/green-campus-au/</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The COVID-19 pandemic contributed to a rise in anxiety among young adults</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mental health among young adults took a dramatic decline in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic. Data from the Center for Disease Control and  Prevention shows trends in symptoms of anxiety among the age group between 2019 to 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stress of maintaining a stellar academic standing, a social life, and an internship or job, among other potential time vacuums, can contribute to feelings of sadness, emptiness, and irritability, all of which were exacerbated by the ongoing pandemic. The vast majority of college students were forced off-campus in March 2020 and made the jarring shift from in-person to online classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time since the great depression, a majority of 52% of young adults lived with one or both of their parents in 2020. For students like myself, this living situation was not chosen, it was forced on us. An inability to socialize with friends and participate in the opportunities offered by college life contributed to a rise in mental health issues for many students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Olivia Alafriz, a sophomore in the School of Communications, living at home was an isolating experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Being inside all the time negatively affected my mood because the lockdown prevented me from seeing my friends. I had no real social interactions for over five months and it was hard not to feel a bit depressed,”” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to her worries was her fear of infecting her immunocompromised 
grandmother, whom she lived with throughout the year. She said she met almost all of her current friends at American through classes this fall and was unable not make many social connections in Zoom classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An annual University of Michigan mental health study found that 66% of 
undergraduate and graduate respondents reported feelings of isolation from others. Social distancing meant students were already at a physical distance from each other, and for most colleges that did reopen in the Fall of 2020, any large social gatherings were strictly prohibited. This made attending college a sometimes even more isolating experience than staying at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethan Dumas, a sophomore at the University of Rhode Island said, “I spent my freshman year on campus but because of the strict social distancing guidelines the only times when I left my dorm room were for meals or exercise. At least at home, I had my dad’s cooking to look forward to every day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side-by-side analysis of data on 18-29-year-olds reporting symptoms of 
anxiety in 2019 and 18-34-year-olds reporting symptoms of anxiety in 2020 shows a dramatic increase in those reporting symptoms after the onset of the pandemic. The data collected by the CDC shows rates of anxiety started at 13.9% in January of 2019 and ended at 13% in December. By May 2020, three months after the first lockdown period began in March, symptoms had increased by a massive 27 points, climbing up to 40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;18-29 Year Olds Reporting Symptoms of Anxiety&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-na5cG&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/na5cG/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;COVID-19 Deaths by Month in 2020&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-p3Ytd&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/p3Ytd/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two spikes in symptoms of anxiety in 2020 occurred in the middle of 
Summer, at 46.2%, and in the middle of Autumn, at 50.2% in November. These spikes may correlate to a rise in deaths associated with the virus, which are tracked by month in the chart below. Over the Summer, the second-highest number of deaths reported occurred over July at 31,118 lives lost. Similarly, in the Fall deaths more than doubled from October to November, climbing to 53,223.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;18-34-Year-Olds Reporting Symptoms of Anxiety in 2019&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-TClcW&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/TClcW/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(e){if(void 0!==e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var a in e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r=0;r&lt;t.length;r++){if(t[r].contentWindow===e.source)t[r].style.height=e.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][a]+&quot;px&quot;}}}))}();&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 U.S. Presidential Election provided another possible source of 
distress for young adults in November. According to a study by the American Psychological Association in October, around two-thirds of all adults (68%) said the election was a significant source of stress in their lives (APA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Zahra Deshaw, a sophomore in the College of Arts and Sciences, living at home proved incredibly draining and worsened the mental health issues she already struggles with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was really bad because I already have mental health problems and my 
siblings also have issues so it was hard for my Dad to manage all of our 
problems at once,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zahra is biracial, identifying as white and Bengali. She said living with her 
white father during the pandemic as the only queer brown woman in the 
household caused immense stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m the only queer person in the family and we lived with our white Dad so that made things even more complicated because we were having all these tough conversations about race with a white person. This made me even more depressed because I didn’t have a brown person to talk with, which made me feel isolated,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zahra is referring to the cultural reckoning with police brutality and racism which occurred over the Summer of 2020. She lived in Portland, OR, one of the epicenters for protests over police brutality, which often turned violent, and she said she struggled with her desire to be part of the movement and her fear of being infected. Ultimately, Zahra decided to attend the protests but said she was extra cautious about social distancing and wearing a mask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Chair of the Psychology Department, Professor Ahrens, “Being a member of an underrepresented group, being queer, in a lot of circles is going to be a chronic stress and if you think about the effects of the additional chronic stress of the pandemic on people who already have chronic stress, you would anticipate that the effects would be stronger.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the intersectional systems of oppression queer women of color like 
Zahra experience, the addition of a new isolating condition to her life posed unique challenges to her mental health. Challenges that she has said have mostly subsided now that she is supported by a network of queer friends in DC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adjustment period for me going from living at home to moving to DC was brief because of how much happier I am living on my own than under my Dad’s roof. I no longer have to walk him through the everyday macroaggressions he subjected me to, whether intentional or not, and that has made all the difference,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked Professor Ahrens for a general assessment of how students mental health levels have changed now that they are back to in-person classes he said, “I’ve certainly heard from many students who just have been so grateful to be back and to see people in person, and it’s, by their reports, made a huge difference. Every student’s experience is different but in general, I see positive trends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a distinct correlation between a rise in symptoms of depression and anxiety among 18 to 29 year old’s and the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. As gathered by my data and interviews, college students specifically experienced worsening mental health due to a switch from in-person to online classes, an inability to socialize with friends, and the feelings of isolation brought on by the first lockdown. The contentious 2020 U.S. presidential election also raised levels of anxiety among young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/young-anxiety-covid-19/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://comm-260.github.io/fall-2021/fall-2021/young-anxiety-covid-19/</guid>
        
        
        <category>mental</category>
        
        <category>health</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
